[Music]
okay so welcome to episode seven of the
inventory tutorial series where we left
off in the last episode we got chest
inventories working so you see that as
we play the game we can walk around and
pick up these objects then we come over
here and access our chests and put
objects in the chests
we've got all the same functionality
where we can split up all of our items
we can back out the chests pick up some
more stuff
go over here
access this chest put our
items in the chest
back out walk away and you know just as
you'd expect it to work
so the one thing that's missing really
is that the player doesn't have a
backpack
and we've only got the hot bar and then
that's it we can't once the hot bar's
full we can't pick up any more
items so the next thing i'm gonna work
on is giving the player a backpack so
when we press b
a similar panel to this will pop up
so we can put things from our hotbar
into our backpack and then
walk away
and close it and carry on going about
our business
and one thing that we i want to add is
the ability so
now once we pick up inventory items and
it'll check the hot bar first and if
this is full it'll move on and it'll
check for a player inventory and then
it'll add themselves to that and this
will help solve another issue as well so
if
if i give this item a rigid body
and then hit play all that's happening
with this pickup script is it's just
looking for an inventory holder
component it's not looking for
specifically a player it's just looking
for
um the chess it's just looking for an
inventory holder script which a chest is
it does have the inventory holder script
on it so so if there was a character
walking around and they accidentally
like you know walked through the item
they'd pick up the item you may only
want it so it picks up the player and
there are a couple of ways we can
solve for that
and one of those is the fact that only
the player has a rigid body
so if they were the only character in
your game to use a rigid body then you
know it wouldn't go over it wouldn't go
into the chest if something with a rigid
body collided with it whereas if it
collided with
the player it would
we could also check to make sure the
thing that hits us is tagged with the
player um player tag that's one way of
doing it but because we're going to be
doing a player inventory holder anyway
we can just make our item pickup look
for
the player script not any other kind of
inventory holder script
so let's just get started on that so the
first thing we want to do is we want to
come over to our inventory scripts and
then we can right click create
c-sharp script
and we'll just call this player
inventory
holder so let's just open up this script
in visual studio so just like our chest
inventory script this is going to
inherit from inventory holder so
inventory holder i'm going to keep the
update so i can uh listen out for a
keyboard press
um and for that i'm gonna want to use
unity engine.input system and we'll look
for when we press the b key and i'll do
that in just a second
the first thing we want we want to uh we
can get rid of the start function and we
just need to serialize uh field
and make a protected int backpack size
so on our inventory holder script we've
got our inventory system which has an
inventory size and i might actually want
to rename this i'm going to right click
double click right click rename
and i'm going to call this the private
primary inventory system
i'll do the same for this rename
primary
inventory system
so in our player inventory holder script
i can actually rename this to secondary
inventory size
oh
and we can have a
serialized field protected
inventory system
and call this the
secondary
inventory system
and then we can have a public inventory
system
called secondary inventory system
which just returns that
and we need to override our awake
function so we've got private void awake
let's just change this to a protected
virtual void awake
so our protected virtual void awake
we're going to make our primary
inventory system but on our player
system
we can do protected override
awake
which calls the base awake so that'll
set up the primary inventory system
and then we can say secondary inventory
system is equal to a new inventory
system with our secondary inventory size
so we're going to use this event this on
dynamic inventory display requested just
like our chest does
and i'm going to listen out for the b
key so if
keyboard dot current
dot b key
was pressed this frame
then we'll just call the on dynamic
inventory display requested
and we'll invoke that and pass through
the backpack the
secondary inventory
system
so let's just hit save there and close
this down so we can go over to our
player script and instead of our
inventory holder script let's remove
this
and let's add in our new player
inventory holder and we give our
primary inventory system which is our
hotbar in this case
uh
and our secondary inventory system let's
give it a size of 30. let's just hit
play
we've got a
error here and it's because we need to
reset our
our player hotbar
needs a reference to our inventory
holder
so now we hit play
that's all working we've got our hotbar
that works we can press b and it'll open
up our backpack
we could pick up some more items
so you see at the moment as we go over
it the items aren't adding themselves to
our inventory backpack
they're staying on the ground
so that'll be the next thing we work on
so let's go back over to our imagery
system script
and back over to our inventory holder
script
so in here on our player imagery holder
similar to our imagery system script
we're going to want a public
ball
add to inventory and this is going to
take in the same parameters as our
inventory systems up to inventory
method so this is going to take in an
inventory item data
called data and an amount
so the first thing we'll do is when we
pick up an item
we'll add it to our um
primary inventory system which is our
hot bar in this case so add to inventory
and pass in the data and the amount
remember this returns true or false
depending on whether it was successful
in adding it to it
so if it was
successful then let's just return
true
because it was successfully added to our
hotbar if it returns false then let's
try and add it to our
secondary inventory system
passing in the data and the amount
and we can just return true if it
manages to go into our backpack
and then we can just return false
if that wasn't successful so let's go
back over to our script here
and what we're going to need to do now
is we need to refactor very slightly the
item script so let's choose an item and
we'll open up our item pickup script so
here instead of saying um
get component inventory holder we can
just get component
uh player inventory holder
because this is a var it doesn't matter
we don't need to uh
make a new type this this still works
and then instead of saying primary
inventory system don't add to inventory
we can just call add to inventory
directly on our inventory holder
and that should just work as is so let's
go back into unity
and we'll hit play
so now as we go over we'll see our
backpack fills up with potato our hot
bar fills up with a potato
and then they start to go into our
inventory
you'll notice though that they don't um
[Music]
refresh while we go over it we have to
open up our backpack again so let's
solve that next to do that let's just go
back over to our dynamic inventory
display and because this works in the
same way as our static inventory display
though where we make a new dictionary
and pair up a ui slot with one of our
system slots
we can subscribe to our
inventory system
method uh
event on inventory slot changed
and where we want to do that is we can
subscribe to it in our assign slot
function so
underneath inventory to display
essentially we can do that in the
refresh dynamic inventory where we
assign our inventory system here
what we can then say is inventory system
dot
on inventory slot changed and then just
subscribe our update
slot
method to it
and just remind ourselves when that's
called it'll look through the slot
dictionary
and if the system slot
exists then we'll update the ui slot for
that ui element so we can come back over
to our dynamic inventory display
and we just want to make sure that this
is valid first otherwise we may get an
error so we can just say if inventory
system
is not equal to null
then let's subscribe to it's on
inventory slot changed
event
let's just copy this
and then when we close the panel
with the escape key we can call on
disable
and we can just unsubscribe from the
event so let's hit save go back over to
unity
so we can pick up all these potatoes
and you'll see that as they start to go
into the inventory
they get
as if it's open while we walk over them
it fills up the inventory
and press escape and close that
come over to our chest
put in the potatoes
and pick up some tomatoes put them in
there
and close that
you see they're all still there we
haven't got any errors in our console
log
and that's not filling up this panel
because this is a different inventory
system so we can close that open up our
bag and there's the tomato that just got
picked up
so that was all working that's a very
simple little change but that allows you
to kind of
carry and walk around with your bags
open so instead of having the backpack
be a dynamic inventory system you could
set it up as a static inventory system
if you know that your backpack's never
going to change throughout the game
in terms of size you could set it up
obviously as a static um
system just like the player hotbar and
then that would allow for
you know positioning say your backpack
up here then you could redesign the
inventory the chest system to come over
here and you may want to move stuff from
your backpack over to your inventory
system so what you could do there is if
we go over to our dynamic inventory
display
and then let's set the constraint count
to five columns instead of ten so it's
not as long it's like half the width and
let's anchor it to the right side of the
screen
and we can drag over the x column so
it's positioned kind of over here on the
right hand side
let's do 450 why not
so we know this is going to be the width
of it
so let's just see what that looks like
when we actually open it up
so we've got our
dynamic inventory displayed there that
was when i pressed b on the keyboard it
opened up that
we could probably move it up a bit as
well
so now let's just ctrl d and copy this
dynamic inventory and let's rename this
to player backpack
and again make sure mouse object is at
the bottom of the hierarchy so it
appears above all of the elements
and let's go over to our inventory ui
controller and open up this
and we need to copy this
and rename it to
my player
backpack
panel
we can just call this the chest panel
instead
actually i'll right click rename so it
changes throughout the code so chest
panel
and then what i'm going to do is i'm
going to go over to our player inventory
holder script
and then go through to our inventory
holder script and i'm just going to copy
this action
and go back to our player in the tree
holder script
and then down here
let's just
say using
unity
engine dot events
so we can get a unity action that passes
in an inventory system and i'm going to
say on
um
player backpack display requested so on
player
backpack
display requested so it's a public
static unity action passes an inventory
system and it's called on player
backpack display requested
and i'll copy this
and i'll just swap out
that event the on dynamic display to the
on player backpack display requested and
we'll go back over to our inventory ui
controller
and here we can say player inventory
holder
dot on
player backpack requested
and we can plus equal and i'll say
display
player backpack
copy that
unsubscribe for it on the on disable
function
let's um
[Music]
copy this method
and we'll say display
player
backpack and what i've done here is i've
said this player player backpack which
isn't what we want so let's just copy
this back up so it's spelled exactly the
same
and it's the chest panel this is going
to set the
player backpack panel
and then again we can copy this
and say
play a backpack panel
so we'll close it if we press the escape
key so let's
now
minimize this and go back into unity
we've got our player backpack which is
in the exact same place as our dynamic
backpack so let's now snap this over to
the left hand side
put the anchor over the left hand side
and we'll drag this across to the left
of the screen
and i'll mirror the y-axis so
we'll just completely mirror this so
minus 450 and then our dynamic inventory
is it
um
i'll say 115.
play backpack 115. so they're at the
same sort of size and height now so we
press play now
nothing happens and i think that's
because we need to go to our image ui
controller
and drag in our backpacks
so player backpack panel goes into the
backpack panel dynamic imagery can go
into the chest panel
is that what the issue was
object reference not set
yeah
and actually let's duplicate um
this and we'll do the same we'll close
the player backpack panel as well
and we hit play
see now we can open our bags that's
going to come up on the left hand side
we can pick up all of our items they'll
go into the player backpack
and we can come over here and we can
open up a chest panel
so these are the two different chest
panels and our backpacks are still open
and we can move stuff from our backpack
into the chests and we can close out of
them go back into the game we can pick
up the
tomatoes off the ground
they've of course gone into our backpack
and then we can come over we can open
our chests we can combine these items
we can split the stack actually and take
two back out come over here
open up this next panel
bring in our tomatoes here take a couple
of tomatoes for potatoes from our hot
bar put them in the small chest exit out
you know take more out so that's all
working kind of as intended
so that's going to be it for this uh for
the initial kind of batch of videos of
this series
if the series does well and it has a lot
of interest and people actually watch it
and want to see more i do have some
ideas of where i'd like to take it
i'd like to introduce um an npc that you
can sell items to from your backpack
because obviously the mpc will need
their own inventory system with a sell
button that um
you know it'll com it'll check all the
value of everything that you're trying
to sell them
and then it'll give you that amount of
gold back so that's something i'd like
to kind of do in the future if this if
this series works and it's well
responded to i'm currently looking into
kind of the best method to save the
backpack system
obviously this video doesn't tell you
how to save and load so if we go back
and hit play obviously everything
everything
resets so i'm currently prototyping how
i personally go about saving this
inventory using json so that'll be kind
of an update to the series as well down
the line if if i can figure out that and
get it in a
concise way to pass that over
one very simple and easy way to do that
is instead of our inventory system
just being a normal class this could be
a scriptable object
so instead of adding um
on the inventory holder
creating a new inventory system here
what we could do is if the inventory
system was a scriptable object like our
items
you could have it so you could right
click create inventory system and then
instead of inventory item you could have
an inventory like underneath it you
could create an inventory put its size
in and then assign that in our um
player holder script
because um
the data in a scriptable object
if you change it that's just how it is
it doesn't reset so if i if i hit play
and if i come over to the potato and i
set its goal size to 10.
so for example if this was a scriptable
object and it was an inventory system
and i had loads of inventory items and i
changed how many i had when you stop
playing
this data stays the same and that that
works even when you build the project as
well so
um a kind of easy-ish way of saving
your inventory systems is to use this go
the scriptable object route but because
i know i do want to build a safe load
system anyway i've gone for
the kind of normal classroom so that'll
be kind of a
an expansion if you will to this series
if if that's what people want if there's
anything else specific that you want to
see in an expansion to this course let
me know in the comments there's always
the project files for this entire course
including all of the scripts from each
individual episode i've exported each
episode's script at the end of that
episode
and if you want to compare your script
to what i've done then come over to
patreon.com and you can get access to
them there if you support me on patreon
if you want to discuss the course or get
help with any kind of elements of this
course or this episode in particular
then again leave a comment below or join
the discord server which is linked in
the description
but in the meantime thanks for watching
and i'll see you in the next one bye
you